- if you a praise the Lord and Happy New
Year for those of - youth who are not
here around the 31st or last Sunday and
welcome to Saddam Valley Road for those
of you who are coming in and you have
not been with us as we have been told
our theme for this year is give me this
mountain give me this mountain I don't
know what that mountain means for you
whatever it is that is our theme this
year which is taken from the words of
Callum in the book of Joshua chapter 14
specifically verse number 12 so we
actually started from the watch night
service
we came to last Sunday and today we are
here today in line with this theme our
topic is developing attack of a spirit
developing attack of a spirit if I was
one of those companies our hashtag would
be taken Lima or Enya qualm Lima or
ponycon am Lima
this is in keeping with the collapse
spirit as demonstrated in various parts
of the scripture God himself referred to
collab as a man with a different spirit
a man with a different spirit when God
sent Moses to deliver the children of
Israel from Egypt God promised to take
them to a land flowing with milk and
with honey but this was not empty land
this was land that was occupied by the
Canaanites therefore literally Moses was
to lead God's people to take over this
land from the Canaanites Moses taking up
this responsibility sent 12 men to go
and survey the land and bring back a
report so they could walk out attack of
a strategy when this man came back ten
of them were unanimous in their report
which is recorded for us in numbers
chapter 13 verse 31 to 33
they said as you read from numbers 13 31
we can't attack those people they are
stronger than we are
and the Bible says they spread among the
Israelites a bad report about the land
that they had explored they said the
land we explored devours those living in
it
all the people we saw there are of great
size
we saw the Nephilim they're the
descendants of anak that come from
Nephilim we seemed like grasshoppers in
our own eyes and we looked the same to
them I want to say that this is not the
report of men who are about to take a
mountain this is not the report of men
who are about to conquer land this is
not the attitude that can conquer
anything the moment you judge yourself
as a grasshopper a grasshopper you shall
be hoping from one thing to another so
this report greatly discouraged the
people they grumbled against Moses and
conspired how they should go back to
Egypt Moses and Aaron was so
disappointed and angry the Bible says
they fell facedown in front of the crowd
devastated but it was at this point that
Joshua son of nun and colep son of
Geffner distinguished themselves as men
of a different spirit as a people of a
different kind the Bible says they tore
their clothes and say to the entire
assembly in numbers chapter 14 verse
number 7 and listen to their report they
said
the land we passed through and explored
is exceedingly good if the Lord is
pleased with us we will he will lead us
into that land a land flowing with milk
and honey and will give it to us verse
number nine only do not rebel against
the Lord and do not be afraid of the
people of the land because we will
swallow them up their protection
is gone but the Lord is with us do not
be afraid of them this now is a people
with a check of a spirit people who are
ready to conquer new territory people
who were ready to take new lands people
who are ready to extend their territory
interestingly as a response to these two
groups of people
God spoke God was so angry with a crowd
the ten people who had brought a bad
report and the whole crowd that had
believed them so don't believe bad
reports you could also be included there
so God saw that they would never enter
the promised land those ten guys plus
those who believed them he said you
shall not enter the promised land but
about calop he had this to say in
numbers chapter 14 verse number 24 the
Bible says
God is speaking and he says because my
servant calleb has a different spirit
and follows me all heartedly I will
bring him into the land he went to and
his descendants will inherit it God says
because calleb has a different spirit I
will give him the land that he went into
and his descendants will take it God
promises to give this land of the
analytes to calleb the land he had gone
into and he was going to inherit it many
years later with a true tech over spirit
and mentality Joshua went into the land
together with the people conquer the
land many cities fell at their feet and
we find now from chapter number 12 they
are distributing the land giving each
tribe their portion
and when it comes to calleb Joshua is
about to give him his portion and calleb
once again proves that is a man with a
different spirit he is not like
everybody else and so as Joshua is about
to give him his portion he refuses he
says no he did not want this conquered
land and so he says in verse number 2 of
chapter 14 verse number 2 of Joshua
which we are going to look at and is a
text of our day give me this mountain
that is our topic what give calleb this
kind of a spirit and how can we also
develop and cultivate this kind of
mentality this kind of tech of a spirit
I see from chapter 14 of Joshua Joshua
chapter 14 we will be looking at verse 6
to 15 and I want to say that there are
three things that I see there that may
have helped Joshua not your show but
calleb to get into this place of
developing a takeover spirit number one
is dissatisfaction
number two is determination and number
three is devotion dissatisfaction
because you see calleb is not satisfied
with ordinary things calleb wants
something different as Joshua allotted
the land
it appears that calleb was not happy
with the land that was going to be given
he approached Joshua and said to him in
verse six you know what the Lord said to
Moses the man of God at Kadesh Barnea
about you and me I was forty years old
when Moses the servant of the Lord sent
me from Kadesh Barnea to explore the
land and I brought him back I report
according to my convictions but my
brothers who went up with me made the
hearts of the people melt with fear
I however followed the Lord my God
wholeheartedly so on that day Moses
swore to me the land on which your feet
have worked will be your inheritance and
that of your children forever because
you have followed the Lord my God
wholeheartedly calleb reveals to us what
drove his dissatisfaction the first one
is the reliability of God's Word color
believed that when God speaks he does
not speak carelessly he does not speak
just like that when God speaks he
intends to fulfill that word so when God
promised color that he was going to
inherit this land calleb hang on to
those words and said if God has said it
that settles it
so for 45 years Connect was waiting for
that time for collab 45 years was not
too long to wait on God's promise for
some of us 45 seconds is too long 45
minutes if we were to make an altar call
for those who want to get healed or even
as we prayed here for those who were to
be healed 45 minutes later you are
feeling nothing what you conclude it
never works
forty-five minutes are too long to wait
for your healing but God says I am the
lord that heals you that is God's
promise but forty-five minutes later we
don't believe it
some of us for five days 45 weeks 45
months live alone 45 years like calleb
collaborative in the reliability of
God's Word a second thing that drove
collapse the satisfaction is the
resoluteness of his conviction calleb
did not move with the crowds this is
where for believers referenda do not
work because the majority are not always
right in the eyes of God 10 out of 12
what percentage is that 10 out of 12 is
more than 80% who agreed we cannot take
that land they unanimously came and said
we looked like grasshoppers in our own
eyes
but two gentlemen did not believe on
that and collapses I brought a report
according to my convictions
now conviction is a very strong word it
is the same word that has the does the
same root as the word convinced so when
I am convinced about something I have a
conviction and that conviction can drive
me to do great and mighty things to go
against the grain to go against what
everybody is saying
and so calleb says I was convinced and I
brought a report according to
my convictions he was a man of
conviction focused on what he believes
we're people saw problems and
difficulties collapse or possibilities
while people killed for handouts collab
focused on his convictions brothers and
sisters we cannot move forward to take
any mountain unless you are convinced
that's despicable there's a Jawad that
it can be taken
you must believe it it may not look like
it but you have to believe that it can
happen the third thing that drove
collapse dissatisfaction is the
realization of his destiny he was he had
a vision when he went in fact I was
thinking about this all my wife has been
pushing me so that we get a mountain it
is true my dear
she loves views you know where you are
up there and you can see yes so we go to
this mountains and we see I say give me
this mountain but I'm like the ten I say
we can't take it but this year we are
going to take a mountain and build our
house on top of a mountain
so that us in our retirement we can be
sitting and looking down there as we
relax and count our blessings and name
them one by one the mountain area in
Kiswahili is called milli money have you
noticed that in any city in any town who
are the people stay in mili money you
know some of you are here some of you
are aspiring this is your opportunity to
say I am moving to Millie money if you
have been in the valley you know the
value of the city collapses I am NOT
going to settle in the valleys I am
going to Millie money and that is where
he is convinced he should go that was
his vision and that vision drove him to
not settle for anything less let me say
that to take over any New Territories
whatever that means in your life we must
be tired of current situations the most
difficult thing in life is to move out
of the comfort zone you know that very
well I know that so very well in all my
life I have lived in three houses since
we got married only three I appreciate
my pasta here who has lived in three
houses in three months he has the Caliph
spirit just just moves for us we are
settlers we go to a place and we we set
off and many of us are like that you go
to a place and you settle and when you
have that kind of a mentality of
settling you cannot move into New
Territories in second Kings chapter 6
verse number 1 and 2 the Bible talks
about some prophets who are dissatisfied
the Bible says in 2nd Kings chapter 6
verse 1 the company of the prophets said
to Elisha look the place where we meet
with you is too small for us let us go
to the Jordan where each of us can get a
pole and let us build a place there for
us to live and Elisha said that is a
great idea go what I like about these
people is that they recognize that the
place where they were living was too
small but unlike canyons or most canyons
they did not go to Elisha and say now
what is this is this the best you can
give us
with all the work we are doing is this
all you can do we don't deserve we
deserve better than this these people
came with a solution I wish people could
come to me with the solutions you know
not just demands in Kenya we make
demands we don't offer solutions the
county governments want more money where
it comes from doesn't matter just give
us more money this repo said the place
where we are living is too small now
give us permission to go to the river
let's go and cut some trees and build a
bigger place who can refuse that Elijah
did not argue did you see that was legis
word was one word go because there is no
that is no problem just go the takeover
spirit is not for men or women who are
satisfied with conquered lands unless
you are dissatisfied with the status quo
you cannot realize the promise of your
destiny because I can tell you possibly
seated in this place are people who are
not happy with their jobs the only
person don't put up your hand because
your boss may be looking you know this
is being broadcast live you are not
happy with where you are working but you
cannot move on because you are afraid
there are people who are live living
under leaking roofs but this is nothing
you know I have no money
you remember one time I talked about it
here people are living in you are living
in a rented house your toilet is broken
but you cannot repair it because it is
not it is not yours but
who sits on that broken toilet it's not
your landlord it is you a toilet is less
than two thousand the last time I
checked about two thousand shillings
why can't you spare two thousand
shillings and buy a new gas they give me
this toilet it has a very big mountain
to climb
no give me this trail it and you live in
a nice house and use it on a nice toilet
some of our toilets have no seat covers
you notice this thing that you sit on
and mix the toilet knives that thing
cost about less than 500 shillings but
you have been sitting uncomfortably on
your toilet because this is not you are
you are not your house you are waiting
for the landlord who is and you know the
landlord is sleeping nicely in the house
say give me this it and you take it
unless you are willing to move from
where you are you will never take your
Mountain some of us are in unemployed
and you have been sitting there waiting
for a job waiting for a job I told our
daughter the other day after she
graduated I told her you know you are
not sitting even if it means roasting
maize just roast maize and sell on the
streets because when you have been
interviewing people when the person
comes and tells us I have been out of
job for five years so what have you been
doing in the five years have just been
sitting then another person equally
qualified both are graduates another one
comes and says I have been looking for a
job but meanwhile hours roasting maize
who'd you the Thule Tech the Mays Rasta
I will take the maize Rosa because what
does it tell me here is a man or woman
with initiative here is a man or woman
who does not mind soiling their hands
who does not mind doing something so
don't just sit there let us say give me
this maize and roast it and sell it you
will not be begging for money this is
also true in a spiritual realm the
desire for more of God will not come by
just wishing I was most spiritual
wishing I could be a better person I
could be a more powerful preacher I
could be a modest be satisfied and seek
out to read the Word of God to go into
the place of prayer to seek the face of
God we are now going into 21 days of
prayer and fasting some of you have
already said I can't like the 10 people
you know that very thought these are on
Akkad's the Anika's have come to church
and they want us to fast for 21 days me
I can't no no no say give me this
mountain and if you never fasted before
we have said basically what you are
saying you don't eat breakfast and you
don't eat lunch but you can eat dinner
shurl is that too hard for 21 days some
people actually live on one meal a day
so it is not even fasting for them
they're saying what are you talking
about that's what I do on a daily basis
so for you now reduce that one meal into
something less can you do that and just
say Lord I have never fasted in my life
but give me this mountain and see what
the Lord can do
spiritual things must be taken in the
same way the second thing that we see in
Joshua is determination attack / spirit
is demonstrated by a determination a
commitment to attain our dreams and
vision because God made a promise to
calleb callebaut m2 Joshua in verse
number 10 and told him and now behold
the Lord has kept me alive as he said
these forty years ever since the Lord
spoke his was to Moses while Israel
wandered in the wilderness and now here
I am this day 85 years old and yet as
yet I am a strong this day as on that
day Moses sent me just as my strength
was then so now is my strength for war
for both going out and for coming in now
therefore give me this mountain of which
the Lord spoke in that day for you have
heard in that day how the Anakim were
there under the cities who agreed and
fortified it may be that the Lord will
be with me and I shall be able to drive
them out as the Lord has said color was
not only be satisfied with the little
handouts that were being given out but
was determined to do something about his
inheritance color did what we call in
leadership and management a
self-awareness test try to find out who
you are and where you are
when he did his analysis he found that
number one he was alive you can take a
mountain if you are dead so he was alive
number two he said he was strong and
number three he said he was killed the
way he went out forward then he said I
can now use that experience to go to war
now the other kites that calleb is once
to confront were among the most feared
in the canaanites tribes as compared
with the Israelites they were tall like
Ganz no wonder these people when they
saw them they said we saw ourselves like
grasshoppers and many believe that the
giant Goliath may have been a descendant
of these people the ANA kites but they
were not just tall and big they were
fierce and they had mighty weapons not
just weapons their cities who are
fortified so it would have been really
foolishness to think that you can go out
and take on the ANA kites but calleb was
not intimidated he looked at himself he
evaluated himself and he saw an
opportunity when you are going to embark
on a major project you do a short
analysis you know the SWOT analysis is
you first do an internal evaluation
those are the first two letters
strengths and weaknesses that is
internal evaluation then you do an
external evaluation the opportunities
and threats so the opportunity was a
mountain the hill country that had been
promised that threats were there uh
naxaiites collapse said I can take it
I can take them he said god help me I
will go out now therefore give me this
mountain but let me say this
dissatisfaction without determination
leads to frustration I am sure there are
many people who are also dissatisfied
with where they are you are dissatisfied
with where you are and you would like
your situation to change but unless and
until you are determined to go out and
do something about it
nothing will happen there is a very
interesting story as this distribution
of land is still going on there was
another group that was very dissatisfied
very dissatisfied just like you're just
like Callum they are found in chapter 17
of the book of Joshua in chapter 17
verse number 14 these are people who are
referred to as the people of yourself I
wondered whether these people of Joseph
because they are grandfather
great-grandfather lived in a palace so
they had a palace mentality so the
people of Joseph also came to Joshua and
the Bible says in verse number 14 the
people just have said to Joshua why have
you given us only one allotment and one
portion for an inheritance we are a
numerous people and the Lord has blessed
us abundantly what were they saying that
because of their large numbers they
deserved a larger portion than they had
been given and now notice how they try
to spiritualize this matter we are a
numerous people and the Lord has blessed
us so who is to blame
the God who has given them a big
congregation like the one of robots
other one is up aspiring to and so he
says we they say we are many you can
give us just one one pusher when Joshua
had this he offered and response was 15
what did he tell them if you are so
numerous Joshua answered and if the hill
country of ephraim is too small for you
that's the birthday they had actually
been given implemented it's too small
for you go up into the forest clear the
land for yourself there in the land of
the paradise and a refights in other
words the land is not all of it
conquered you remember we said that last
Sunday so there is still more land to
clear so go out there and clear more
land and take for yourselves what did
they answer the people in verse number
16 the people of Joseph replied the hill
country is not enough for us and all the
Canaanites who live in the plain have I
on chariots both those in best shun and
the settlements and those in the valley
of Jezreel
what were they saying that in spite of
their numbers they were not strong
enough to fend for themselves they
wanted land that was already conquered
they wanted handouts while calleb at 85
years he's saying we are ready to take I
am ready to take fortified cities of the
a naxaiites the people of Joseph with
all their blessed numbers are afraid of
the Canaanites
invasion why because the Canaanites had
iron
Joshua got mad at these guys
I can imagine him walking away from
these parasites and told them in verse
number 17
you are numerous and very powerful you
will have not only one allotment but the
forested country as well clear it and
it's fathers limits will be yours though
the Canaanites have iron chariots and
though they are strong you can drive
them out hallelujah now do you see the
difference between Caleb and Joseph
Joseph wants handouts you have only
given us one piece and we are so many
they are told the land is still large go
and take they say no no no you know
those that land is occupied by people
with ion chariots
Joshua comes and now dust for them as
what analysis Caleb did it for himself
Joshua does it for them what does Joshua
tell them Joshua tells them you are
numerous you are powerful you can go out
there and take this you are strong in
fact it says in the last part and you
can drive them out you have the capacity
they are not happy they are not happy
my time is up let me say this if we are
to enjoy a better life we must arise and
clear the land nobody owes you anything
your destiny is in your hands you are
powerful you are strong go out and clear
the land and take it get into some
unexplored territory get into some place
that people have not gone like Joshua
told these people clear it and their
fathers limits will be yours in
leadership and management there is
something called the blue ocean
anybody heard of the blue ocean as
opposed to the red ocean and it is said
that businesses that become market
leaders operate in the blue ocean this
an alloy is taken from analogy of the
Sharks and the wealth in the shallow
waters that is where all other fish and
animals are found and they fight for
space they fight for territory in that
space in the shallower waters out of
that fighting blood flows and this blood
makes that water red that's why it is
called red ocean where everybody is
fighting for space but they are sharks
and whales who live that area and they
go into the deep blue sea
where others fish cannot go and there
they have freedom they can move around
as far as they want they can go into
deep waters and eat whatever they want
because they have freedom and so
businesses that really get to be market
leaders go into spaces where there is no
competition they go into areas and
fields where nobody is you know in Kenya
as Kenyans and I'm one of them
we love the red ocean if somebody has
discovered quills what happens we all go
for quills and the water is muddied very
soon quills is no longer business do you
ever hear equals anymore no it's dead
because all of us went there somebody
discovers me Tomba me tomba is
everywhere someone discovers is
everybody is there now people who move
ahead go into the deep blue sea they
there is no competition so Joshua is
telling this this Joseph's men go into
the bluest blue sea blue ocean area and
clear the land it will be us brothers
and sisters as I read this was a
challenge for me and I'm thinking to
myself where is my blue ocean where is
my blue ocean blue ocean can only come
to you when you have number-3 devotion
devotion
when Joshua saw what Caleb was
determined to do the Bible says in verse
number 13 verse number 13 then Joshua
blessed
calleb son of Jonah and gave him heparin
as his inheritance
so heparin has belonged to collapse son
of Geoff nitaac in sight ever since
why because he followed the Lord the God
of Israel whole heartedly you will not
capture the blue ocean you will not
conquer your Mountain unless the Lord is
on your side hallelujah what was the
reason given for Calum successful
capture his territory
it was not because of dissatisfaction it
was not because of sheer determination
the reason given in verse 14 is because
he followed the Lord the God of Israel
whole heartedly one thing that is
mentioned about Caleb over and over
again is that he followed the Lord
wholeheartedly in Joshua chapter 14
verse 8 he says my brothers who went up
with me made the hearts of the people
melt with fear I however followed the
Lord my god
whole heartedly in Joshua chapter 14
verse number 9 he says so on that day
Moses swore to me the land on which your
feet have worked will be your
inheritance and that of your children
forever because you have followed the
Lord my god whole heartedly in verse
number 14 it is recorded so heparin has
belonged to color son of Jeff now the
cancer it ever since because he followed
the Lord the God of Israel whole
heartedly
you can go to the blue sea and die there
nobody will even find you altogether so
don't venture into the blue sea if the
Lord is not with you don't venture there
and you say now I'm venturing into
business and nobody has ever done hey my
friend we'll just be hearing news
perhaps we may we may not even hear that
you disappeared now yes it's also where
did he go
the last we had of him he was studying
this strange business but we have never
heard of him
again because he went and this sank in
the deep blue sea but if you who follow
the Lord whole-heartedly
hallelujah you can take heparin yep Ron
will be yours so as the people of God we
must recognize that without God we
cannot do anything Jesus himself told
his disciples I am the vine and you are
the branches if a man remains in me and
I in him he will bear much fruit
hallelujah but that is not the end of
Jesus sentence it says apart from me you
can do nothing there are many of us who
will readily say amen to those words of
Jesus and yet go ahead and leave the
opposite depending on their own hard
work Jesus said in John chapter 15 verse
16 if anyone does not remain in me he is
like a branch that is thrown away and
with us such branches are picked up
thrown into the fire and burned
brothers and sisters the year is fresh
hallelujah
it is like canon which part of this year
are you going to take the one that is
already cleared or the one that is
available and God promised you this year
is pregnant with opportunities this year
is pregnant with great ideas it is when
we go to the Lord and say God what is
your word for me this year this is what
I am sensing in my spirit I want to take
this mountain but unless you go with me
I'm not leaving this place let me tell
you brothers and sisters come December
you will be standing here to give a
testimony you'll be standing here to
give a testimony of what the Lord has
done so it is not just the satisfaction
that's where it begins but it is not
just determination that is what propels
it it is also devotion to God whole
heartedly we follow the Lord
wholeheartedly pray to God and say Lord
if there is anything that can get me out
of you take it from my spirit take it
from my heart if there is anything that
can derail me from walking with you this
year take it away from me but help me O
God that I may follow you whole
heartedly seek ye first the kingdom of
God and all these mountains shall be
added unto you
let us pray together
[Music]
you